Outer Banks History Center Ephemera Collection PC.5276
State Archives of North Carolina
Outer Banks History Center Ephemera Collection
1798-2019 and undated
PC.5276
37.010 2.000
The Ephemera Collection, 1798-2019 and undated, contains ephemera (printed documents, created for a specific, limited purpose, and generally designed to be discarded after use) primarily related to the state of North Carolina and its counties, with a particular focus on Dare County. The collection was assembled over a period of several decades by Outer Banks History Center staff. Materials primarily document the history of Dare County and the State of North Carolina. Several notable Dare County organizations (such as the Roanoke Island Historical Association), events (such as the Pirates Jamboree and commemorations of the Wright Brothers' first flight), businesses (such as hotels, restaurants, and retail stores), and other entities are documented in the collection. The collection especially focuses on the tourism industry in North Carolina, both on and along the North Carolina Coast and throughout the state. Additionally, the collection includes historical materials relating to the University of North Carolina System and materials created by national and federal entities, such as the United States Coast Guard.
Outer Banks History Center
Box Box 1
Box Box 2
Box Box 9
Box Box 10
Box Box 11
Box Box 12
Box Box 13
Box Box 14
Box Box 15
Box Box 16
Box Box 17
Box Box 18
Box Box 19
Box Box 20
Box Box 21
Box Box 22
Box Box 23
Box Box 24
Box Box 25
Box Box 26
Box Box 27
Box Box 28
Box Box 29
Box Box 30
Box Box 31
Box Box 32
Box Box 33
Box Box 34
Box Box 35
Box Box 36
Box Box 37
Box Box 38
Box Box 39
Box Box 40
Box Box 41
Box Box 42
Box Box 43
Box Box 44
Box Box 45
Box Box 46
Box Box 47
Box Box 48
Box Box 3
Box Box 49
Box Box 50
Box Box 51
Box Box 52
Box Box 53
Box Box 54
Box Box 55
Box Box 56
Box Box 57
Box Box 58
Box Box 4
Box Box 59
Box Box 60
Box Box 61
Box Box 62
Box Box 63
Box Box 64
Box Box 65
Box Box 66
Box Box 67
Box Box 68
Box Box 5
Box Box 69
Box Box 70
Box Box 71
Box Box 72
Box Box 73
Box Box 74
Box Box 75
Box Box 76
Box Box 77
Box Box 78
Box Box 6
Box Box 79
Box Box 80
Box Box 81
Box Box 82
Box Box 83
Box Box 84
Box Box 85
Box Box 86
Box Box 87
Box Box 88
Box Box 7
Box Box 89
Box Box 90
Box Oversize Box 1
Box Oversize Box 2
Box Box 8
Item Outer Banks History Center Ephemera Collection
Folder paper
Arrangement
The Ephemera Collection is arranged into four series: North Carolina Counties, 1798-2019 and undated; State of North Carolina, 1825-2016 and undated; University of North Carolina System, 1857-2010; and United States, 1932-2016. The first two series are further divided into subseries.
Access Restrictions
Available for research.
Biographical/Historical
The Ephemera Collection was assembled over a period of several decades by Outer Banks History Center staff. Materials in the collection dating prior to the 1990s appear to have been collected primarily by David Stick, while materials from more recent decades were collected and added by individual Outer Banks History Center staff members. The collection primarily documents the history of Dare County and the State of North Carolina. Several notable Dare County organizations (such as the Roanoke Island Historical Association), events (such as the Pirates Jamboree and commemorations of the Wright Brothers' first flight), businesses (such as hotels, restaurants, and retail stores), and other entities are documented in the collection. The collection especially focuses on the tourism industry in North Carolina, both on and along the North Carolina Coast and throughout the state. Additionally, the collection includes historical materials relating to the University of North Carolina System and materials created by national and federal entities, such as the United States Coast Guard.
Custodial History
The Ephemera Collection was assembled over a period of several decades by Outer Banks History Center staff with donations received from various donors. Much of the collection appears to have come from David Stick. Most materials from the 1990s-2010s were received in the mail or collected from community events by Outer Banks History Center staff members.
Dare Coast Pirates Jamboree Collection from the Outer Banks History Center,(collection 5305)
Scope and Content
The Ephemera Collection, 1798-2019 and undated, contains ephemera (printed documents, created for a specific, limited purpose, and generally designed to be discarded after use) primarily related to the state of North Carolina and its counties. The largest portion of the collection documents Dare County and its organizations, businesses, and events. Materials in this collection include brochures, pamphlets, flyers, event programs, posters, articles and clippings, circulars, campaign flyers, memorabilia, reports, and other printed material documenting the state of North Carolina from the mid-19th century to the present.
The Ephemera Collection is arranged into four series: North Carolina Counties, 1798-2019 and undated; State of North Carolina, 1825-2016 and undated; University of North Carolina System, 1857-2010; and United States, 1932-2016.
Green, Paul, 1894-1981--Lost Colony
North Carolina State University; Roanoke Island Historical Association; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; University of North Carolina (System)
Flight--Centennial celebrations, etc.; Real property--North Carolina--Dare County; Recreation--North Carolina; Tourism--North Carolina; White Supremacy Movements--North Carolina
Dare County (N.C.)--History; Dare County (N.C.)--Societies, etc.; Kill Devil Hills (N.C.)--History; Kitty Hawk (N.C.)--History; Manteo (N.C.)--History; Nags Head (N.C.)--History; North Carolina--Centennial celebrations, etc.; North Carolina--Description and travel; North Carolina--Environmental conditions; North Carolina--Exhibitions; North Carolina--History--19th century; North Carolina--History--20th century; North Carolina--Politics and government; North Carolina--Race relations; Outer Banks (N.C.)--Description and travel
- North Carolina Counties, 1798-2019 and undated; 43990; Outer Banks History Center
  Scope and Content
  The first series of the Ephemera Collection contains materials related to North Carolina's local communities, businesses, organizations, and events. These materials are arranged by county. The documents in this subseries primarily consist of promotional flyers, brochures, event programs, pamphlets, clippings, and other ephemera related to individual businesses, organizations, or other entities within each county. The largest subseries in this series contains documents related to Dare County, including materials on the Roanoke Island Historical Association and The Lost Colony, travel guides created by the Dare County Visitors Bureau and Outer Banks Visitors Bureau, political ephemera, pamphlets and brochures related to real estate and vacation rentals in Dare County, and information on local churches.
  - Alamance, 1959-1992 and undated; 4663; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Alamance)
  - Ashe, 1888, circa 1970s; 4675; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Ashe)
  - Avery, circa 1970s-1996 and undated; 4676; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Avery)
  - Beaufort, 1905-2006; 4677; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Beaufort)
    - Beaufort (General), 1967-2006; 22948; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Beaufort (General))
    - Bath Historic Site, 1963-circa 1990s; 22949; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Bath Historic Site)
    - Businesses, circa 1990s; 22950; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses)
    - Organizations, 1955-2005 and undated; 22951; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations)
    - Ye Olde Bath Towne Souvenir Calendar, 1905; 22952; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Ye Olde Bath Towne Souvenir Calendar)
  - Bertie, 1956-2002 and undated; 4678; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Bertie)
  - Bladen, circa 1970s-2000s; 4679; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Bladen)
  - Brunswick, circa 1950s-2013 and undated; 4680; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Brunswick)
    - Bald Head Island, 1984-2013 and undated; 22953; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Bald Head Island)
    - Brunswick Town State Historic Site, undated; 22954; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Brunswick Town State Historic Site)
    - Businesses, circa 1950s-1999 and undated; 22955; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses)
    - Southport and Oak Island [folder 1 of 3], 1979-1999 and undated; 22956; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Southport and Oak Island)
    - Southport and Oak Island [folders 2-3 of 3], 1979 - 1999; 22957; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Southport and Oak Island [2 folders])
  - Buncombe, circa 1950s-1994; 4681; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Buncombe)
  - Burke, undated; 4682; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Burke)
  - Cabarrus, 1957; 4683; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Cabarrus)
  - Camden, 1971-2004; 4684; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Camden)
  - Carteret, 1906-2015 and undated; 4685; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Carteret)
    - Businesses, 1906-2015; 22958; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses)
    - Businesses: North Carolina Maritime Museum, 1989-2007; 22959; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses: North Carolina Maritime Museum)
    - Hotels and Accommodations, circa 1920s-1997; 22960; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Hotels and Accommodations)
    - Organizations [2 folders], circa 1950s-2011; 22961; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations [2 folders])
    - Organizations: Beaufort Historical Association, 1990-2004; 22962; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Beaufort Historical Association)
    - Organizations: Core Sound Decoy Carvers Guild, 1992-2003; 22963; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Core Sound Decoy Carvers Guild)
    - Organizations: Duke University Marine Lab, 1991-1993; 22964; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Duke University Marine Lab)
    - Organizations: Mailboat, 1990-1993; 22965; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Mailboat)
    - Petition by Fishermen of Carteret County, 1917; 22966; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Petition by Fishermen of Carteret County)
    - Recreation, circa 1950s-1992 and undated; 22967; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Recreation)
  - Catawba, 1959 and undated; 4686; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Catawba)
  - Chatham, 1984; 4687; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Chatham)
  - Cherokee, undated; 4688; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Cherokee)
  - Cherokee Indian Reservation (Jackson/Swain Counties), 1963-circa 1980s; 4689; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Cherokee Indian Reservation (Jackson/Swain Counties))
  - Chowan, 1798-2007 and undated; 4690; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Chowan)
    Includes a document approving travel for a local citizen, Arthur Jones, and guaranteeing against the spread of smallpox during the Edenton smallpox outbreak of 1798.
  - Columbus, undated; 4691; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Columbus)
  - Craven, 1883-2004 and undated; 4692; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Craven)
    - Businesses, 1977 and undated; 22968; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses)
    - Organizations, 1883-1999 and undated; 22969; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations)
    - Political Ephemera, 1908-1912; 22970; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Political Ephemera)
      Contains flyers for gubernatorial candidate Locke Craig, who ran on a white supremacy platform in the 1912 election.
    - Tryon Palace, circa 1970s-2004; 22971; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Tryon Palace)
  - Cumberland, 1889-1986 and undated; 4693; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Cumberland)
  - Currituck, circa 1950s-2013 and undated; 4694; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Currituck)
    - Businesses, 1960s-1999 and undated; 22972; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Businesses)
    - Organizations [2 folders], circa 1950s-2013 and undated; 22973; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations [2 folders])
    - Organizations: Committee for a Mid-County Bridge, 1992; 22974; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Committee for a Mid-County Bridge)
    - Organizations: Corolla Academy, 1961; 22975; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Corolla Academy)
    - Organizations: Outer Banks Conservationists, 1995-2008; 22976; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Organizations: Outer Banks Conservationists)
    - Real Estate, 1985-1997 and undated; 22977; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Real Estate)
    - Recreation, 1995-2003 and undated; 22978; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Recreation)
  - Dare, 1881-2019 and undated; 4659; Outer Banks History Center
    Dare County materials comprise the largest subseries in North Carolina Counties series. Materials in this subseries were largely created to in support of the Outer Banks tourism industry, and primarily consist of pamphlets, brochures, event flyers, and other promotional material. This subseries includes documentation of the Roanoke Island Historical Association and The Lost Colony, travel guides created by the Dare County Visitors Bureau and Outer Banks Visitors Bureau, political ephemera, pamphlets and brochures related to real estate and vacation rentals in Dare County, and information on local churches.
    - Organizations, 1914-2019 and undated; 4660; Outer Banks History Center
      This subseries contains materials documenting various Dare County organizations, clubs, and groups. Materials primarily consist of promotional brochures, flyers, and event programs, although some folders may contain meeting minutes or other administrative material.
      - Algonquian Indians of North Carolina, Inc, 2004; 4695; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Algonquian Indians of North Carolina, Inc)
      - Bicentennial Committee, 1976; 5001; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Bicentennial Committee)
      - Chamber of Commerce, 1980-2014 and undated; 5002; Outer Banks History Center
        - Small Business Expo Programs, 1992-1999; 23044; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Small Business Expo Programs)
        - Business After Hours, 1992-2014; 23045; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Business After Hours)
        - General, 1984-2011 and undated; 23046; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General)
        - Seminars and Meetings, 1980-2006; 23047; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Seminars and Meetings)
      - Circus Tent, Inc., 1977-1985 and undated; 5003; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Circus Tent, Inc.)
      - Coastal Wildlife Refuge Society, 1990-2013 and undated; 5004; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Coastal Wildlife Refuge Society)
      - Creative Puppet Ministries, 1984-2014 and undated; 5005; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Creative Puppet Ministries)
      - Dare County Arts Council [2 folders], 1982-2016; 5006; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County Arts Council [2 folders])
      - Dare County Arts Council, 1982-2016; 5007; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County Arts Council)
      - Dare County Board of Realtors, 1967-1978; 5008; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County Board of Realtors)
      - Dare County League of Women Voters, 1993-2015; 5009; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County League of Women Voters)
      - Dare County Organizations (general) [2 folders], 1914-2017; 5010; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County Organizations (general) [2 folders])
      - Dare County SPCA, 1973-2013 and undated; 5011; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare County SPCA)
      - Dare County Tourist Bureau, 1955-2012; 5012; Outer Banks History Center
        - Banquet, 1969-1994; 23048; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Banquet)
        - Calendar, 1992-2006; 23049; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Calendar)
        - General [2 folders], 1955-2012; 23050; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General [2 folders])
        - Outer Banks Vacation Guide, 1967-1974; 23051; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Vacation Guide)
        - Outer Banks Vacation Guide, 1975-1982; 23052; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Vacation Guide)
        - Outer Banks Vacation Guide [4 folders], 1983-1999; 23053; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Vacation Guide [4 folders])
      - Dare Education Foundation, 2006-2010; 5013; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare Education Foundation)
      - Dare Voluntary Action Center, 1989-2013 and undated; 5014; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dare Voluntary Action Center)
      - Dunes of Dare Garden Club, 1968-1995 and undated; 5015; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Dunes of Dare Garden Club)
      - First Flight Society, 1943-2015 and undated; 5016; Outer Banks History Center (Folder First Flight Society)
      - First Flight Society Commemorations, 1941-2005 and undated; 5017; Outer Banks History Center (Folder First Flight Society Commemorations)
      - Freedmans Colony Preservation Association, 1996-2013 and undated; 5018; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Freedmans Colony Preservation Association)
      - Friends of Jockeys Ridge, 1991-1995 and undated; 5019; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Friends of Jockeys Ridge)
      - Friends of Nags Head Woods, 1991-2001 and undated; 5020; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Friends of Nags Head Woods)
      - Friends of Roanoke Island, 1974-1995; 5021; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Friends of Roanoke Island)
      - Hatteras Island Organizations, 1984-2005 and undated; 5022; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Hatteras Island Organizations)
      - Icarus International, 1984-2010; 5023; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Icarus International)
      - Kill Devil Hills Organizations, 1995 and undated; 5024; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Kill Devil Hills Organizations)
      - Kitty Hawk Organizations, 1958-2003; 5025; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Kitty Hawk Organizations)
      - LegaSea, 1989-2003; 5026; Outer Banks History Center (Folder LegaSea)
      - Man Will Never Fly Memorial Society, 2003 and undated; 5027; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Man Will Never Fly Memorial Society)
      - Manteo Lions Club, 2010-2011; 5028; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Manteo Lions Club)
      - Manteo Organizations, 1951-2014; 5029; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Manteo Organizations)
      - Nags Head Chamber of Commerce, 1962-1969, 2005 and undated; 5030; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Nags Head Chamber of Commerce)
      - Nags Head Organizations, 1994-2006 and undated; 5031; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Nags Head Organizations)
      - Nags Head Taxpayers Association, 1970; 5032; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Nags Head Taxpayers Association)
      - Outer Banks Community Foundation, 1988-2018; 5033; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Community Foundation)
        - Annual Meeting Programs, 2003-2017; 23054; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Annual Meeting Programs)
        - Annual Reports, 2002-2018; 23055; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Annual Reports)
        - General, 1988-2012; 23056; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General)
      - Outer Banks Forum for the Lively Arts, 1983-2015; 5034; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Forum for the Lively Arts)
      - Outer Banks Homebuilders Association, 1984-1996; 5035; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Homebuilders Association)
        - Builders Guide, 1989-1995; 23057; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Builders Guide)
        - Parade of Homes, 1984-1996; 23058; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Parade of Homes)
      - Outer Banks Hotline, 1997-2010; 5036; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Hotline)
      - Outer Banks Lighthouse Society, 1996-2013 and undated; 5037; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Lighthouse Society)
      - Outer Banks Surfriders, 1995-2005; 5038; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Outer Banks Surfriders)
      - Outer Banks Visitors Bureau, 2003-2015; 5039; Outer Banks History Center
        - Travel Guides, 2003-2005; 23059; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Travel Guides)
        - Travel Guides, 2003-2015; 23060; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Travel Guides)
      - People to Preserve Jockeys Ridge, 1974-1975; 5040; Outer Banks History Center (Folder People to Preserve Jockeys Ridge)
      - Roanoke Colony Memorial Society, 1926-1937; 5041; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Roanoke Colony Memorial Society)
      - Roanoke Island Business Association, 1960s-2007; 5042; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Roanoke Island Business Association)
      - Roanoke Island Commission, 1994-2014; 5043; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Roanoke Island Commission)
      - Roanoke Island Historical Association, 1934-2019 and undated; 4661; Outer Banks History Center
        The Roanoke Island Historical Association (RIHA) is primarily charged with overseeing the annual production of Paul Green's symphonic outdoor drama, The Lost Colony, at the Waterside Theater in Manteo. Most of the materials in this subseries relate to historical productions of The Lost Colony, including programs, playbills, event programs, and publicity. Included in this subseries are the program and playbill for the inaugural performance in of the production in 1937. In addition to The Lost Colony materials, this subseries also includes documents related to RIHA as an organization, including early promotional and membership materials from the mid-1930s.
        - General, 1934-2013; 4739; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General)
        - Roanoke Island Learning Center, 1998; 4740; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Roanoke Island Learning Center)
        - Membership, 1934-2014; 4741; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Membership)
        - The Lost Colony, 1937-2019 and undated; 4662; Outer Banks History Center
          - 60th Anniversary Reunion, 1997; 22996; Outer Banks History Center (Folder 60th Anniversary Reunion)
          - Backstage Tour, 1990-1992; 22997; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Backstage Tour)
          - General [2 folders], 1937-2015; 22998; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General [2 folders])
          - General [2 folders], 1937-2015; 22999; Outer Banks History Center (Folder General [2 folders])
          - Playbills [3 folders], 1937-2012; 23000; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Playbills [3 folders])
          - Playbills [2 folders], 1937-2012; 23001; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Playbills [2 folders])
          - Playbills, 2018; 23002; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Playbills)
          - Professional Theater Workshop, 1992-2006 and undated; 23003; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Professional Theater Workshop)
          - Programs, 1937-1963; 23004; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Programs)
          - Programs, 1964-1977; 23005; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Programs)
          - Programs, 1978-1996; 23071; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Programs)
          - Programs, 1997-2019; 23072; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Programs)
          - Promotional Posters, 1964-1997 and undated; 23073; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Promotional Posters)
          - Publicity, 1938-2018; 23074; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Publicity)
          - Student Synopsis, circa 1970s; 23075; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Student Synopsis)
      - Roanoke Island Organizations, 1965-2007; 4742; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Roanoke Island Organizations)
      - Southern Shores Organizations, 1984-2002; 5048; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Southern Shores Organizations)
      - Theatre of Dare, 1997-2015; 5049; Outer Banks History Center (Folder Theatre of Dare)
    - Businesses, 1901-2018 and undated; 4664; Outer Banks History Center